welcome to
voices with raviki so i have a very
special guest uh today
uh so my guest is jinson kim let me tell
you a little bit about ginseng i first
met him uh teaching him a high school
class
on classical civilization uh a long
a long time ago um and then he came to u
of t
and did cognitive science uh with me
um and now he is a ta um
in uh i think at least two of my courses
right now
um uh on ra um he's also a collaborator
where
we we write papers together we uh make
craft presentations together he's also
my my lab manager
uh for the consciousness and wisdom
studies lab uh so
uh junsung is um currently a graduate
student working with michelle ferrari
as his official supervisor and with me
as sort of an unofficial supervisor
uh he he he refers to michelle and me as
his mom and dad
i think i'm the mom i'm not i'm not
quite happy about that but nevertheless
um it's it's great to have him here and
jon song's career is just taking off
right now
you recently got a major publication in
a premier journal
let him talk about that in a sec but he
um
has taken up the torch if that isn't
condescending to him i mean it is a
compliment
of doing the cognitive science of
religion and spirituality and his own
research is just taking off
and so i'm just really excited to have
him here
so welcome jinson thank you it's it's
good to be here
um so yeah um i'm jung i have
uh worked under for
and with john for nearly a decade now
geez let's not think about that too hard
and uh yeah as mentioned my particular
areas of specialty
are the cognitive science of
spirituality of religion
of uh lifespan development um
by and large my own area of research can
be
summarized as the study of intentional
growth
so my focus is
on ways in which people can change and
develop
on purpose as opposed to you know
psychological growth being something
that just happens to you as a result of
fate or circumstance or accident my
interest is in the ways that people
can take charge of their own development
so
this has of course led me through
research in mindfulness
research in spiritual practices research
in
magic and mysticism a little bit of
research in
the martial arts we do need to finish
that paper
yes and um so that's where i'm coming
from all of this
um i think my thinking is i'd say
50 john's fault and 50 the fault of
myriad other influences who i've had the
good fortune of being able to study with
over the last 10 years
so it i mean i like i said i think if
ginseng more is
more family um so
what i want to talk about uh which is in
the purview uh voices with vervice the
is the work so you mentioned a paper you
and i are working on work
working on which we need to finish a a
naturalistic account of the
key phenomena or the chief phenomena
within the internal martial arts and
uh related healing modalities um
you've done some work with uh michelle i
know
on people's use of the i ching
and you've been recently doing quite a
bit of work
on uh what you call the cognitive
science of magic
now you don't mean by magic anything
involving supernatural
horses i know you have a paper that's
under review right now
i forget which site journal it is uh
that is so that that one's the uh the
journal of trans personal psychology
actually but um i think the seeds of
that
line of thinking so sure let's let's
jump right into it
what do we mean by magic here um the
seeds of that line of thinking can
actually be found in another publication
that michelle and i just got accepted in
the humanistic psychologist
right which is on the history of the
psychology of religious experiences
so what we do in that paper is we
track the phenomenological study of
religion as compared to the sociological
study of religion which is a little bit
more constant through history
to shall we say three separate waves you
have the
original wave at the kind of end of the
19th beginning of the 20th century
with william james edwin starbuck
and you know some of the actual great
original luminaries in the history of
psychology
um then it fades away a little bit
as experimental behaviors and becomes a
dominant paradigm
um because you know as we reason
it is very difficult to induce a
religious experience in the laboratory
you know um we've had some success
recently with psychedelics inducing
mystical experiences but as we get into
in the paper
the extent to which those are religious
experiences under a strict definition is
not clear
right right um and then
there's also the ironically increasing
development of psychology as a science
leading to a lack
of careful familiarity with
philosophical tools religious and
spiritual literature
and the just general toolbox you would
need to actually study a religious
experience
um so ironically as a watsonian vision
of
psychological science becomes dominant
your toolbox to study certain phenomena
degrades rapidly
we then find that this comes back in the
post-war era with the work of
young and maslow and the kind of great
humanistic existential psychologists
who start to become a little bit more
interested in individual experience
actually there's um somebody uh
points out in one of their books i can't
remember who it is off the top of my
head unfortunately
that psychology the psychology of
religion and the psychology of sexuality
almost
switched places over that 30-year span
oh interesting
where um you know william james writes
an entire
classic on the psychology of religion
and two pages on human sexuality
uh at the dawn of the 20th century but
then
uh kinsey who's writing in this kind of
40s 50s and 60s period
writes you know text after text after
paper after paper about human sexuality
and nobody's talking about religion um
so you know that is yet another boom of
the psychology of religious experience
and here you start to see the beginnings
of what i think is important to
understand in any sort of cognitive
science of
magic or spirituality which is
a decoupling of the
theoretical from the practical um
i'm especially using those terms to
hearken back to
james fraser's uh distinction between
theoretical magic and practical magic
right right where you have your
underlying metaphysics and ontology of
the
entities at play your
explanations of how things work you know
what you would call the language of
training versus the language of
explanation
right so and you see this earlier
in um john dewey's work uh he starts to
mention this but it really starts to get
taken up by especially maslow
this idea that religion and spirituality
as practices do not require the
supernatural as a theory to function
right right right yes so
that's where you start to see these
things kind of peel apart
and then we kind of characterize the
current era of research
on mystical experiences and religious
experiences
as really being defined by that final
cleaving
between the experience and the
interpretation
right right right um you know we do get
into
well is this really the right idea can
we actually distinguish experience from
interpretation
um you know i think one of our recent
experiments demonstrates pretty handily
that that's a really
tough nut to sell yeah yeah that's right
right
but you know this is this is kind of
where the field is going
so when i'm talking about the cognitive
science of magic what i'm interested in
is essentially
looking at how much of the practical
side
of spirituality of religion of magic of
mysticism
of all of these practices that have
traditionally relied on the supernatural
can we replace their theoretical side
with good cognitive science
right right right right right with
you know this almost this approach
almost gives us a sort of a touring test
right where
if the idea of a touring test is a
sufficiently advanced artificial
intelligence
excuse me if a sufficiently advanced
artificial intelligence
should be able to perfectly mimic human
interaction
then practices
derive from a cognitive scientific
interpretation of magic
right should be able to replicate the
practices of a traditionally trained
magician
right right right right yeah um from
what i've seen that might be a tall
order and we might be 40 or 50 years out
but i think it's manageable at some
point
so i like this this move you're making
because it's obviously
right you know about deeply trying to
bridge between cognitive science
and the part of that family
mysticism magic religion and
spirituality that is often
the one that is held up as the exemplar
of irrational behavior
uh kookiness uh superstitious
supernatural metaphysics
etc um and so your
if if i understand you correctly and i
you know i i read some of your work and
participate in it with you so i hope i
do you march
yes yes um you know
you're doing something analogous to what
i tried to do and it's in the awakening
for the meeting crisis around shamanism
and try and say without adopting the
shaman's
metaphysical view can we understand both
the phenomenology and the functionality
of shamanism
what's happening in the altered states
of consciousness why that might
facilitate
healing why it might improve hunting so
i take it that you're doing something
analogous and
like that and extended from that is that
is that a fair uh
yes i'd say that's that's that's a
pretty accurate interpretation
especially because
i think the work on shamanism was kind
of the seed idea for this
right right um where you know if you
look at the
history of human spirituality shamanism
is kind of the the er art the proto art
right um it is magic it is spirituality
it is mysticism it is religion it is
science it is mindfulness all
wrapped into this singular bundle of
kind of original human psychological
technologies
yeah and as you know i agree with matt
rosano
and uh michael winkelmann and
david lewis williams that you know
shamanism is
probably the psychotech the ecology of
practices
that really drove uh the huge cognitive
leap
happening in the upper paleolithic
transition uh so
even though that does not in any way
give scientific evidence for the truth
of shamanistic metaphysics
it does say that the phenomenology and
the language of training
within chinese is doing very very
powerful things
so can you can you give me an example
several examples let's
just go crazy jim son of how you're
bringing this work to
you know various practices that have
been called magical and and some of the
cog sigh around them
sure so oh boy where do we want to start
here
um i think i think it might be good to
start historically actually
um to kind of give people a bridge from
shamanism
into magic and mysticism proper and then
go from there sure please so
you know um something that i'll
occasionally say to people when they ask
me why i'm studying magic is you know
my argument is that magic is a human
birthright
it is i would say the oldest
faculty we have that really
distinguishes us from the other very
complex tropic animals
right right um you know if it is true
that shamanism was the driving factor in
the upper paleolithic revolution
then magic is why humans are the
dominant species on earth
um which is going to be a very strange
sentence
for a lot of people listening to this
yeah yes but
hear me out so there are
direct lines to shamanism that you can
find throughout history
that evolve in one way or another and
actually i would say you can
characterize the axial revolution
um as essentially the
filtering and formalizing of certain
aspects of shamanic psychotechnology
relative to the culture that the
revolution is occurring in ah
well said so in ancient greece for
example
um you know the sociological pressures i
think are very well
laid out in awakening from the meaning
crisis so
i won't go over them here but you get
the powers of watching the natural world
of looking for fixed points of abstract
reasoning and
symbolism just condensed
through uh pythagoras through socrates
from the thracian shamanic tradition
just kind of almost as a series of
lenses focusing sunlight into something
more concentrated and powerful
not quite as broadly applicable but you
do
get this very very powerful
psychotechnology that is
excellent at picking up the constants in
the natural world right
right right now
if you go to india what i think the the
vedas
represent is another concentration
of shamanic practices but these are the
shamanic practices
for shall we say internal
phenomenological manipulation
right right um you know
yes basically the manipulation of one's
own consciousness
is kind of the the filtered ability and
you could even argue
that what you get in the abrahamic
tradition
is kind of the concentration of the
power of
narrative from the shamanic tradition
yeah right right um
and china i would say is
you know they're they're a little bit
more manifold i think the
but the psycho technology that i would
say is par excellence in china is the
capacity for tracking change
right right um you know you get this
through the classic of changes you get
this in a very
biodynamic approach to medicine um
you get this and it's very interesting
to track the evolution of chinese
science versus
greek science because greek science is
very focused on constants in the natural
world whereas chinese science is very
focused on dynamics
all right so you see that even in like
the the the
sort of the flow within tai chi chuan
and things like that
yes yes um
yeah so i would say you know the ability
to track and effect
change is what really goes on
in the uh the chinese segment at the
chinese
um the axial revolution in china
right so you know the reason why i'm
going through all of this is because you
do kind of see
this splitting of the original shamanic
psycho technology
right into forms of psychotechnology
that become
shall we say mainstream right right
right now this especially becomes
clear in ancient greece and roman europe
um but we get the word
magic from the greek word
for persian especially zoroastrian
priests
right nice so
the term magic
has its origins in a word meaning the
psychotechnologies of the other
right yeah the significant other for
greek culture too
yes yeah and you know the um
in in chinese for example the word for
magic and the word for shaman and
pretty much the same thing um you know
it depends on who you talk to there is
this word for magic that largely means
otherworldly there's also a word for
magic that means shamanic
um but you know basically the
[Music]
the shaman's tool kit fractures
depending on where you go in the world
right and especially in you know greece
and
greek intellectual descendants the
non-kosher parts of it shall we say
become magic but they're still part of
this same toolkit
right okay that's why um so
when i am referring to magic i am
essentially referring to
the entire toolkit i don't use the word
shamanism because i would
reserve the term shamanism to refer to a
very raw form of this toolkit in its
original integrated context
right right because in the thousands of
years between
shamanism and magic magic gets
complicated
right right right right the symbolism
becomes incredibly diverse
incredibly rich incredibly complex the
rituals diversify and specify
you know if you look at um
medieval grimoires for example they are
complex instruments right right um
and you know the the classic
grimoire and this is the case no matter
where you go in the world there are
chinese grimoires there are indian
grimoires
um currently taking a look at a hebrew
grimoire which is a
an interesting lark um and you know this
is kind of why i want to say
like magic is everywhere magic is just
the
complexified historical descendants of
ancient shamanic psychotechnologies
so uh is it fair to say then
that there are still sort of broadly
given the way you've described the
origin sort of three domains
in which we could see sort of psychotech
for
altering states of consciousness kind of
coming you know
and in that sense technically
mindfulness practice would be a kind of
magical practice
right yes i think mcclellan in his book
the
wisdom of hypatia says that magic is the
art of being able to
change consciousness at will yes yeah
um that's that's not wrong actually um
if you'll allow me this comparison
yeah the core disciplines of stoicism
of logic ethics and physics right
actually i think make an excellent
framework to
split magic right people have to
understand that
logic for the stoics means much more not
just what is now logic today i mean it's
much more like psychology
yes you know just basic reasoning skills
like
if you twisted my arm a little bit i
would say
that from original shamanic magic
the greco-roman tradition inherited
logic
the uh vedic tradition inherited ethics
and the chinese tradition inherited
physics
right but what i was going to do that's
great
but i was going to say you these are
sort of domains where you're
transforming consciousness yes
and domains where you're trying to pick
up on what is most constant
unless people think that's only a
scientific practice one way of
understanding mysticism is to try and
get at
you know the ground of being the
ultimate reality which is the most
constant
and then you also have the ability to
try and track
changes and you know this has been
picked up more recently
uh you know in 40 cognitive science
where you know
alicia arrow talks about the use of
narrative
right in order to yes turn your
cognition into something like a
dynamical system so you can better track
the dynamical systems of the environment
the ecology
uh and so um is that a fair way of
parsing it so
that you could look at sort of
psychotech for sort of
tracking dynamical systems psychotech
for transforming consciousness
and then psychotech for trying to get at
sort of what is most constant
in reality is that is that fair yeah
yeah i i'd say that's fair and you know
you find forms of magic that work for
all of them like every magical tradition
contains a meditative tradition
yeah um in terms of just trying to kind
of ground out your own
um ground out your own issues but then
you know you get
divination for tracking patterns there's
this
fantastic project going on at harvard
that they call predictionx
which is an attempt to
collate and systematize every way that
humans have ever tried to predict the
future
and it goes all the way from babylonian
horror spiky
all the way to modern stats right right
right
and i just love seeing the things just
put on the same graph
because they're completely right that's
all we're doing
so this picks up on sort of the
predictive processing um
yeah and you know you and daniel thank
you greg you have been
talking about that um yes um what you're
doing yeah
so the the way that i would um
kind of build on that other definition
of magic as the ability to
kind of change consciousness at will is
magic by and large is using techniques
of imagination to
bootstrap powers of cognition yeah that
i think that is very well said
and that goes well with the predictive
processing model because it sees
imagination basically
as the top-down predictive aspect and
and and sensation of perception is sort
of the bottom-up
yes yeah well and you know and this is
why i think we've had this conversation
i think we need to go back to a more
aristotelian
way of looking at the imagination yeah
where
you know the senses do not integrate in
and of themselves you have this
what they refer to as the common sense
yes that sticks them all together
but you have control over that common
sense so you can stick senses together
in all sorts of ways
so that uh look getting disciplined
practices
that you could train to be able to
transform
that common sense would then impact on
the kinds of patterns
you were able to pick up on within
yourself within others and within the
world
um and and make and and sort of uh
couple to the world in more powerful
ways is that
also a way of understanding what we're
talking about here yes absolutely and
you've heard me talk about this before
you can only process things you can
imagine
right yeah so the more limited you are
in scope of your imagination ultimately
the less
rational you are yes i agree with that
um
and you know people like to rag on
practices of imagination as being
irrational and fancy and things like
that
you know it's a little bit like saying
going to the gym
is an artificial recreation of tasks you
will actually have to perform in the
world
yeah that's true you still go to the gym
because it expands your base capacity to
do things in the world
right right so that that that's that's a
very
yeah i like the gem or or the dojo
analogy uh
so well that sort of segues into what i
wanted to ask you which is
you know there's a lot of people who are
probably watching this and they have
knives out
um and they're they're looking for a
indiana
in any way i mean there's two groups
there's there's the people who are sort
of
uh are self-designated as being rational
um and then you said there's an
important relationship
between imagination and rationality
and i like i've said before i think both
the calvinist and the romantic
understanding of imagination are sort of
are defective by
being different kinds of extremes uh so
i can see
right that the rationalist coming in and
saying that this is all just
superstitious crap
and then i can hear religious people
coming in and saying
this is all just heresy uh et cetera et
cetera
so let's let's do the first group first
because i think that's where
um like a lot i mean that i i know
you're respectful of religious
traditions but
i can tell in a lot of the work you're
really wrestling with those who come in
uh uh it's like i said self-designated
as the defenders of rationality
um and say you're why are you doing this
this is all just
there's one there's a simple explanation
for all of this which is people are just
superstitious and irrational
and that if they were just rational and
usually the implicit
thing is rational like me uh then you we
we we
need to do any of this but you've been
trying to show um first of all how
pervasive it is
and how functional it is and that like
you said it's possible to
understand the functionality without
committing to the metaphysics
so like i said can you give us some of
those arguments
so i think my first argument to the
skeptic as far as rationality goes
is it's not going away
yeah you know this is if you read the
works of rossano
of winkelmann of tanya lerman um
you know uh actually most of whom i've
met and are all fantastic people
yes um sorry just at a weird point in my
life
um this is just part of human makeup and
if you read uh jason josephsome storm
has a fantastic book
called the myth of disenchant right and
i will yet again say
uh jason joseph storm has one of the
best names i've ever heard
yes um it's a fantastic name for a guy
who studies magic
anyway his point is that you know we
like to pretend we are living in this
world of disenchantment you know
post uh weber's whole point about
uh the great disenchantment and things
like that which i would argue
you refer to as the disembedding because
they're functionally the same thing
right yes um and joseph storm's point is
no we're not if you look at the
statistics of who believes in the
supernatural who believes
in um esp who believes in aliens and
things like that
proportions have not changed in over a
hundred years
um you know
science is great but you know magic has
always existed in the cracks
um actually i think my favorite finding
of his
is that who believes
like the proportion of the population
that believes in one thing versus
another thing has not changed in the
last couple of hundred years
but what's funny to him is that the
belief systems are mutually exclusive
for example people who believe in
psychics do not believe in witches
that's i didn't know that that's very
interesting well because
basically the argument is that like
these people have constructed a coherent
system to explain
how these things work and like i've
looked at
the um
uh the the esp kind of framework um
you know i prefer the magic framework
because it's older and has a little bit
more generalizability
but yeah if you believe in uh
people who are psychokinetic you don't
need magic
it's all psychokinesis um
meanwhile if you believe in magic you
don't need psychokinesis it's all magic
um so the reason why i start there
is because you know let's
let's be honest you know humans are not
born inherently rational
um at least not the way that people tend
to use that word
what people are born with is a capacity
for utilitarian pattern funding right
so you know basically
what all of these people who believe in
some supernatural thing or another
are doing is they are having experiences
that science does not do a very good job
of explaining or addressing
and they are attempting to patch them
into a world view right
now what because i've even encountered
scientists who are like
i don't know man i found this thing and
it's weird
um you know part of scientific training
is the ability to
sit with doubt and mystery um
i'm i'm not knocking that i'm not
knocking scientific training i think
it's important i've got 10 years of it
yeah um you know 10 years of it under a
very good teacher
but
this isn't me saying that superstition
or the supernatural
is necessary it's
me saying that it's an understandable
part of people trying to figure out a
way to actually
live and work and act in the world
because
one of the things you know you can't
just have pure language of training
right you have to have some sort of a
language of explanation
right right and right
yeah i'd say the biggest issue is is
you know um michelle
my you know supervisor on paper um
he's a big believer in what william
james referred to as radical empiricism
yeah if a human can experience it you
must be able to study it
right no there has to be some sort of
underlying systematicity to human
experience
even if the way that a human experience
something is completely non-replicable
right right like you know the uniqueness
of identity being a thing it could be
that there are there is no plausible way
that anybody else
will ever have this like one experience
it's a little bit like
um my dad was telling me his story cause
he's a big baseball fan
of uh this guy who he
hit the ball and it lined up just
perfectly so that a
bird flew in front of the ball right as
it was going down the pitch and you just
see this explosion of feathers
as the universe lines up just right for
this ball to hit the bird
that's never going to happen again but
under the laws of physics it
can happen so james's argument is that
even if it's never going to happen again
under the laws governing human
experience it is clearly possible
for it to happen so therefore we must be
able to understand it somehow
if we want to assume there's some sort
of systematicity and
i do have to say mainstream science does
a terrible job
at cleaving to that kind of a thing
a lot of academics a lot of people who
claim to be rational
and i will say claim to be because you
know i
do believe that you need to have a
sufficiently powerful imagination in
order to be properly rational
because otherwise you're looking at the
world with one eye shot yeah
so you know and you know we know this
people are not good judges of their own
rationality
yes yes um so
you know i guess my rebuttal to the
pseudo-rationalists is twofold one
is the practical consideration
of people are having experiences that
systematically track something you know
like
uh all the wiccans that i've talked to
like you know they do the rituals and
something happens
right um and you know i've um
been hanging out with a sufi group for
part of the last year and
that's a very powerful experience and
yes you do experience
something yes and uh
you know they need to have some sort of
system to put it all in because
otherwise how do you share it
and the second part of my rebuttal is
if your argument that something is not
rational is that you have not personally
experienced it nor can you conceive of
it happening
that is a poor argument yes the
world is huge people are diverse people
are capable of having all sorts of
experiences that you will never have
so so that's that's good um
so a third argument i want you to apply
to is
yeah but the only reason this persists
is just because people are persistently
stupid and irrational
and i get it that's still question
begging because of your previous two
arguments
but i think you also have an independent
response to that you want to say
well there's another explanation for the
persistence i don't think you deny that
there's some self-deception going on in
these things and
people are playing power politics and
doing all the all all kinds of stuff
with oh absolutely and people do that in
science people do mean
science people do that in art people do
that in politics so sometimes let's
let's just acknowledge that
self-deception is random okay putting
that aside
you you say yeah independent of that i
think you say
there's another uh important
reason for the persistence of what
you're calling magic
namely is it has important functionality
it transforms people it enables them to
learn
it enables them to aspire it enables
them to access
aspects of the psyche or their own body
or psychosomatic interaction
sorry i apologize i might have left that
implicit in my previous answers but
the bottom line is this stuff works
yeah um it may not work in the exact
way that the metaphysics that they're
holding up says because you know we've
known since the 1950s from arthur
rieber's work that people cannot explain
their own pattern finding
yeah yeah yeah they cannot it does not
matter how rational you are
you cannot explain your own pattern
finding um i
am sure with a sufficient amount of time
and training you might be able to do it
but people are just bad at it um so
let's let's yeah let's forgive that as
just
part of human psychology that's
unfortunately slightly unavoidable
and let's be a little charitable and
point out people do not
keep things that do not work right um or
at least
let me rephrase that people do not keep
things that do not
perform some sort of a function
right even if that function is just
nostalgia
um so you know and
we're finding increasingly like we're
cleaving off pieces of
shamanism and magic and turning them
into clinical psychology
over and over and over again you know
we're taking psychedelics we're taking
ritual we're taking you know mindfulness
practices and things like that
right right every time we have taken
something from
magic and changed its metaphysics into
science
suddenly it works yes yes yes
hear me out it's not the change in
metaphysics that's making it work
yes yes very well said very well said
uh although perhaps the change in
metaphysics this is going to be a segway
to my last
next question allows you to bring
science to bear and perhaps reverse
engineer or improve it
to some degree yes and so you know i've
i've joked about this for years where my
entire tagline is sufficiently analyzed
magic
so this this brings me to the question
which is it's
out i mean i know this from your work
but just so just to give you an opening
here
like so cognitive science especially for
e-cognitive science
plays a special role in doing that in
you know in re-situating
these practices and explaining their
functionality and perhaps affording
in enhancing uh their functionality so
can you talk a little bit
about that please so so this will
actually require me to backtrack a
little bit because
um sometimes it is the change in
metaphysics that allows it to work
um actually the the first publication
that i was ever on
was on um
the influences of the prosperity gospel
on risk-taking behavior
right right right and one of the
findings
particularly sticks out to me um
and you know i i thought this was clever
on behalf of the first author
uh nick hobson who he he studies ritual
he's
uh he's a good guy um
anyway the finding was so you know
we uh well i i helped mostly with the
theory bit so during data collection
participants were exposed to a
clip of joel osteen preaching the
prosperity gospel
and you know lo and behold they found
that okay um
you know exposure to hearing the
prosperity gospel makes people
indulge in risk-taking behaviors as um
you know tested through a gambling task
afterwards
does that mean that they have to
explicitly believe in
the sort of so here's the thing
is they did this in a follow-up study
where they split it into
atheists and theists right and then made
two versions of the recording
one of them was the original recording
and the other
was the recording scrubbed of any
mentions of god or the bible or what
have you
right um you know original recording was
you know preacher uh giving a sermon and
the scrubbed recording was designated as
motivational speaker giving a talk right
here's the kicker if you scrub
everything out of the
uh you know if you scrub god in the
bible out of the recording it works on
atheists
[Laughter]
there was an amplified effect for the
prosperity gospel and theists
suggesting that there is more of a
buy-in effect the more you buy into it
right right but you know this is where i
do kind of have to backtrack on
my own it's not the change in
metaphysics that makes the thing work
but it is the change in metaphysics that
makes the thing accessible which is what
allows it to work
ah that's better that's much more um
precise
and helpful thank you so the metaphysics
um there you might we might even think
this is just occurring to me now the
metaphysics has sort of an explaining
function
but it also has this new function you
mentioned it gives you an accessibility
function
it allows you to access the pro the
practice from your particular world view
is that yeah that's interesting i hadn't
thought about that so there might be
three languages there might be a
language of training
there might be a language of explaining
and then there might be a language of
accessing
or making it accessible that's
interesting well there's a there's
perspectival language right
right yeah participatory perspective of
language yeah right
underneath all of this you have to have
the basic way in which you're looking at
the world that allows certain things to
be possible versus impossible
right just the basic filter of relevance
realization
right needs to be set up in a particular
way right now
granted you know it's uh one of those
things where i know anderson does this a
lot and i've gotten into it you need to
learn to play with your own metaphysics
of what's possible versus impossible
right um you know if you don't have
certain grounding practices and you know
unfortunately not to get political or
anything but
not interrogating your own world view is
what allows people to be manipulated
um yeah yeah you know especially through
conspiracy theories and things like that
right because if you look historically
um part of the proper
education of a shaman or a magician or a
spiritualist or anything
is learning to warp your own field of
possibility
and find your way back right right you
know it's especially to find your way
back bit that's important
and you know this is why you find a
meditative tradition in every single
magical tradition
because you need a grounding practice to
be able to find your way back to reality
or at least whatever reality you're
working with so
so that's good could you give another
example perhaps the work you did with
michelle
like on the eye chain or the work you're
doing with me on on she
about science can explain these
phenomena that p
explain both the phenomenology and the
functionality
in an integrated fashion sure um so
actually let's let's do the iching one
just because that's top of mind and
because it's a classic example of magic
that everybody wants to dismiss out of
hand
that they can't dismiss out of hand for
two reasons one they don't know what it
is
and two they don't know how it works
right um
so the i ching is probably going to be
heard properly the eating is
going to be familiar to most people as a
manual of chinese fortune telling
um very famously translated by wilhelm
and baines and commented on by young
the jungian commentary is terrible um
you know i say this with all due respect
he was a psychologist bound to a certain
place in time did not have certain
resources available to him
but um you know i
speak like kindergarten first grade
level
mandarin and read classical chinese
decently due
to having an education in chinese
philosophy
one of our co-authors my lab mate anne
is fluent
so we were able to actually access the
classical chinese sources
and young's commentary does not hold up
if you look at the classical literature
anyway so but the operative you know we
kind of used the itching uh the aging as
a lens because
it was convenient and interesting and
that's what we had access to
but the argument works for all forms of
divination so
first things first fortune telling does
not do what you think it does
um and you know this is uh i've studied
with the wicked church of canada for the
last year as well to kind of get the
emic understanding on magic as well
right and they are also very clear on
this
divination does not tell you the check
is going to be in the mail next tuesday
right um what
divination does and this is
uh this is a difficulty thing to explain
outside of either chinese or neoplatonic
metaphysics
but most magical systems
look at the natural order of
life fate the universe the planet and
things like this as kind of an ongoing
river
individual human choices can vaguely
shape the flow of the river
but you know ultimately a river flows
one way
right what divination
practices allow you to do
is gauge what's happening downstream
um especially practices like tarot card
reading or itching divination
are essentially acts of
i find myself at a crossroads i could
act this way or i could act this way
assuming i act in one particular way
what kind of consequences am i looking
at downstream
what do i need to avoid what could
possibly come up
things like this like the itching is
especially full of this because a lot of
its
readings are things like you know well
superior a superior person would do this
a foolish person is going to have this
happen to them don't do this
right um so and the wiccans especially
are very clear on never ask divination
for specifics never go
fishing in a divinatory system it
doesn't work that way
um so you know that's
so how does it work then like i mean
scientific terms because that's what
we're trying to do here
so let's go back to that reaper stuff
that we were talking about before
right so we know that people are
terrible at
you know gauging their own pattern
recognition right you know what people
are not terrible at
pattern recognition itself right uh
people are fantastic
at finding hidden patterns yes um and
you know unfortunately this has ruined a
lot of research in the past right like
if there's
any sort of pattern in your randomized
scheme people will find it
we found this with the blind site
research you know
um all sorts of things humans are
fantastic at implicit pattern
recognition i
doubt there is anything on the planet
that is better than we are right
um implicit meaning that they can detect
and this is what reverse show
they can pick up very complex patterns
without being aware that they're doing
so or knowing how they do so
even if they become aware that they're
doing so right
you know this is just a thing we do as
humans right
now let's say we're back in the day
and you don't have modern statistical
software
or things like that to do your
prediction
right the human faculty for implicit
pattern recognition
is your best tool for predicting the
future in fact arguably that's what it's
for you know
um the two hunting strategies that
humans developed
both necessitate the capacity to predict
the future
right because our hunting strategies are
chase something until it dies of
exhaustion
right so we need to predict where the
thing is going or
throw rocket moving target which also
requires our ability to predict where
the thing is going so basically this
thing
is very very well developed for
predicting future events
right um you know this is hypotheses
this is
telling this you know predicting the
weather this is basic if this then that
right right and what reaper showed is
that we do this on a level so implicitly
that we can't actually figure out what
the heck we're doing
skip to the work of keith oatley which
is
he looks at narrative as a sort of
modeling software
right right so you know you
read fiction and it allows you to you
know practice that kind of predictive
ability
right so fiction i mean in that sense is
part of what you're talking about
this training of the imaginable faculty
i mean one of the reasons why we read
great literature
is it trains our imagination so we're
much better at understanding other
people
picking up our patterns intuitively
about how they're moving
around in the world what they're
thinking what they're seeing what
they're believing but people don't just
people don't just they just don't label
that as magic
no they don't they should but they don't
right um
you know especially because if and
here's where we'll get into things
the purpose of a divination system
is to create an
artificial grammar right um you know and
this is one of the reasons why i
rag on astrology a little bit because it
requires a reach to construct an
artificial grammar because part of the
point is that it needs to be randomized
and astrology is a closed system i kind
of treat astrology as the magical
equivalent of genetics
um yeah anyway so what you're doing when
you're casting lots or drawing cards or
things like that
is you are creating an
artificial randomized symbolic grammar
right
which allows you to you know when i'm
describing this in light persons terms i
describe it as fly paper for thoughts
right um you know this is a fantastic
instrument unfortunately
it is notoriously fickle it is you know
um this is why people meditate right
like
think about pink elephants and think
about nothing but pink elephants for
the next five minutes it's not
possible yeah um not without
massive powers of concentration that
take decades to train
so what you're doing with a
divination tool is you are creating a
structure out there in the world to
project your imagination onto
so that you can bootstrap the
association game that your brain plays
with
everything to project narrative order
onto your implicit pattern recognition
right and this well and and then aliso
gerardo also talks about
how narrative gets our mind working in a
way that's very good at picking up on
complex dynamical systems
because of the way narrative you know
layers things and has those
you know uh feedback and small
differences and context sensitivity and
blah blah blah blah blah yes so you get
to use
basically what you're doing is you're
bootstrapping a few different things
here you're bootstrapping
basic complex pattern recognition right
narrative processing which allows you to
massively accelerate the
complexity of the information that
you're dealing with
right and symbolism right and i think as
you've discussed in other videos
symbols are very powerful because they
allow you a very
complex multi-apt thing to stick pieces
of cognition to
yeah so they don't have to carry them
around in your head yes right
that's right so and you know there's a
ritual element to divination as well
right
um and you know this is where
traditional wiccan literature and nick
hobson's work overlap
is the thing that ritual is fantastic
for is regulating emotion and shaping
intent
right which also then impacts on the
even the
the bioenergetic aspects of cognition
and consciousness
i wanted to ask you about the randomness
because i mean
you and i have done related work on this
too i mean israel reminds me of you know
uh and daniel talks about this too and i
talk about it too
you know the disruptive strategies for
inducing insight or yes
or in neural networks how you throw
noise into the system
uh so you prevent it from overfitting so
if you use your kind of language
you you open up the the space of
patterns
that you can yes yeah it's you know
there's
basically there's both a selective
constraint and an enabling constraint
going on
in the process of divination there is an
enabling constraint that
massively expands the number of patterns
that you can possibly be
processing once right um and you know
there's
uh certain like certain forms of
meditation they teach you to kind of
like let go
of the grip that you've got in your
reasoning so active imagination
essentially gets massively accelerated
um you know the symbols having
qualitative
uh fluid meanings rather than strictly
defined fixed meanings also has an
impact on this
semiotic drift yeah but the
randomized element and
the ritual setting creates a
selective constraint on the divination
process so it's basically kind of one of
those like
you know let's say that you could
normally come up with three patterns
select one right
um what divination allows you to do
is instead of going you know draw three
pick one
it's draw ten pick four right right
right right right
right so it's you know a basic strategy
for massively expanding the number of
patterns that you can hold at once
and artificially constraining the
selection process
so that you don't go essentially
um you know essentially so you don't go
into choice paralysis
so i mean using sort of a mcgilcus
language you're doing a lot of
you know really enhancing a dynamic
shifting between left and right
hemisphere
yes and you know we know that that
happens with
literacy anyway right yeah um you know
tarot cards are words let's
let's put it that way or at the very
least they are both under the subset of
symbol that require and you know you
read tarot cards in a very similar way
that you read words on a page right and
you know you read the itching the same
way where you do have to kind of do this
dynamical back and forth
between individual symbolism at an
individual level and symbolism in a
contextual level
so this reminds me of stuff from the
neoplaton tradition like you know uh
you've read it too uh gregory shaw's
work on their gear
yes right and the symptomatic practices
where they would be given
sets of objects and then they had to try
and find the symptomata
the pattern that they all like they all
symbolically belong to
and so yes and then you what you do is
increase the variation
and then people and and and this reminds
me and
you know where i'm going this reminds me
of sort of the deep learning strategy in
neural networks
where you introduce variation and then
you try and find the underlying pattern
that's invariant and then from that you
introduce there and this is how the
brain actually
learns and how artificial intelligence
so yes
so and this is also why if you look at
medieval grimoires
right the section of the text that is
not specific spell formulae
which by the way um i once heard spell
formula i described as synesthetic
equations and that is essentially what
they are
right um there is somebody yeah there is
somebody in the itching literature who
has described the iching as
qualitative binary notation
um which i think is correct right
basically what you do is you form a
synesthetic association between
symbols and certain qualities and the
symbolism allows you to
rearrange especially if you have a
particularly powerful imagination
allows you to rearrange you know certain
quality sensations emotions feeling
so that you know okay based on the
grammar of the symbol
this is the state that i need to be in
in order to achieve this thing
um but it will dispose itself in
different ways is that yeah
yeah yeah sorry but what i was
originally saying is the section of
um spellbooks that are not those
formulae
are giant correspondence and association
right right right right right
because they basically they allow you to
make more and more and more and more
associations based on increasingly
subtle or occulted symbolism um
by the way if this sounds like a
children's game um
you know we've had this discussion
before there is a reason
so many tests of cognitive flexibility
look like children's games
yeah yeah um because children are way
more flexible than an adult is ever
going to be and you need
constant practice in order to maintain
that flexibility so
the itunes then using this language uses
sort of multiple
intervention psychotech to massively
increase cognitive flexibility
right but in this like you say in this
systematic fashion
and this allows people to better like
tap
into their capacity to tap in
exact and improve their capacity for
picking up on implicit patterns and
that's how they
sort of divine like the the course
or something like that yes now
of course it is kind of one of those
things where you know you talk about an
ecology of practice a lot
yeah the reason why like even within a
divination practice there's a bunch of
things going on right
right there is you know you're usually
supposed to meditate a little bit before
you engage in divination um the wiccans
especially have a code of ethics where
there is no divination without
contemplation
um you do not employ magic until you're
at the end of your cognitive rope
right right right um because you know
if this sounds like a recipe for
potentially going insane
that's because it is right um
you know as we talked about i just want
to do your slogan because i think it's a
really good one
you talk about how magic is a tool it's
not a toy yeah
you know i'll say a lot rule number one
magic is not a toy
um rule number two is magic and money
don't mix
yeah um but you know rule number one is
magic is not a toy because you are
playing
with very very old very very fundamental
psycho technologies
for manipulating your ability to
perceive and predict
patterns in the world yes um this can
very readily either
essentially paralyze you for life with
choice paralysis as you see
everything um you know or you just start
seeing things that aren't there
yeah yeah yeah so i mean one of the
uh and i mentioned theater from the new
platonic traditions is you see
you see this i mean so the pairing
between theorgy and philosophia you see
this
you know that you all you have both
these ritual practices
and then you have these practices that
are uh designed to train rationality in
more comprehensive sense i argue for
of systematic ways of overcoming
self-descending
enhancing you know the religious
coupledness to the world
but you see you see the theorgia
especially after i
after i am booked in proclass and
demacias
right you see the theoria and the
philosophy are
always deeply into defined
interdependence yes and you never
practiced them
um and you know this is this is one of
the reasons why i get angry at people
in the science versus spirituality
debate
you can't have one without the other
right right
right you know like um
something that i desperately want to
write a book on at some point is almost
the spiritual ethics of curiosity
right right um because i'm sorry you
can't be an uncurious scientist
um you know there is
deep deep moral and existential import
to being able to look at the world with
awe
and reference in the wood rough line of
things and just say
this is so much bigger than me yeah but
the spiritual practices are what allow
you to
relate to that in an important way yeah
right rather than just referring to it
as well
exactly like they're what let you tie
yourself into the world
um you know it's uh
michelle and i have another paper uh on
the way with
um monika adult which looks at the
kind of relationship between wisdom and
well-being as mediated through
spirituality
yeah and increasingly what's becoming
clear is what the sense of spirituality
tracks
is your sense of connectedness to
something bigger yeah which is um i've
been arguing
like wow as you know yeah and actually
funnily enough i was at a
uh i participated in a round table
through the wiccan church of canada
a couple of weeks ago kind of on the
topic of what is magic
and something that came up is magic is
both craft and
feeling it is the feeling of
connectedness of pattern of things
clicking together and something
happening
as well as the craft of being able to
bring about that feeling
right right right that's very
interesting i was just going to point
people to
and i'm going to have brian on it
sometime but we've been doing
work with you know discussion with brian
ostepan and he's been
doing some experiments about how awe
really improves
uh sort of your cognitive flexibility
your ability to pick up on patterns
uh yes and then you and i uh with
jennifer stellar and with michelle
we're crafting an experiment to see uh
where we're predicting that we're going
to see that
ah has important beneficial effects
which makes sense
because we experience awe as a
tremendously rewarding
experience people will often designate
it as one of the most significant
experiences of their lives
and you know that this is if you'll
forgive me for interrupting
one of the things that so frustrates me
about
scientists in general is if you look at
the
original intention behind the study of
physics
in the hellenistic world
and you know let's do my favorite thing
and
hop continents because this is how you
see that something is real
neoconfusions have the very similar
practice the entire point
of what the neoconfusion is called
invest the investigation of things or
you know um physics in the west what
the thing that eventually turned into
science and natural observation
the point is awe right
the point is not to do in the wizard and
you know
not you know measure the marigolds and
things like that
the point is to encounter the sheer
size and scope of everything and just
let it open you
yeah um and this is why i would say you
know you have to
there can't be signs without
spirituality i think if
and you know this this gets me in
trouble with colleagues sometimes
because
um i do treat science as sacred in a
very old sense of the word
yes yes um yes i wonder where i got that
one from
so this this is really interesting and i
mean i i could
you know there's connections here to the
work that daniel's doing and the work
that anderson anderson todd's doing
uh a bunch of we talk about this
regularly yeah
and so i mean we're just sort of uh
you know just the tip of the iceberg
kind of thing going on here so
what's next for you uh
i mean you know what's supposed to be
next for me is finishing my thesis the
phd thesis
yes yeah um you know this kind of
ties in here because um
you know michelle called me on this
because one of the things that i want to
do
so um the core of my uh
phd thesis is on you know callard's
notion of aspirations
right yeah and the development of wisdom
and essentially you know are things like
wisdom and self-transcendence things
that you pursue on purpose
or does you know having a more
coherent purposeful approach
to living life predict the development
of these things
right um and of course can we affect
that in the classroom can we affect that
in workshops things like that
right um but you know the
goal kind of going forward is okay
but you know how does the sense of
realness
fit into this right like yes yes um you
know if
because what we're finding is um you
know the first wave of my thesis
research
kind of found actually that the 3dws
monica's version of personal wisdom and
the swis igor's version of wise
reasoning
seem to be tracking two different
narratives regarding wisdom
right um if you consider wisdom as
you know freedom from pain freedom from
anxiety and a very buddhist
kind of notion of um
i wouldn't even say buddhist notion
because the actual buddhist notion of
prajna has very little to do with this
yeah yeah um but if you do kind of view
it as a very
like you know the cessation of worldly
suffering you know to be wise is to
not suffer worldly pain um
that's one narrative of wisdom and
monica's uh
measure seems to be tracking pretty much
that right right what
igor's measure seems to be tracking is
wisdom in terms of the pursuit of active
growth
right right we've kind of described it
as the negative narrative and the
positive narrative there's the i don't
want to be this way narrative which is
tracked by the 3dws
and there's the i do want to be this way
narrative which is tracked by the swis
oh that's interesting they track
different things for example
uh the 3dws the negative wisdom tracks
you know um freedom from stress
um i think a little bit more sense of
control things like that
whereas igor's measure attracts more
things like meaning
you know like what you get out of this
kind of thing um
it's kind of like the epicureans of the
stoics yes
yes uh yeah i would say that um
yeah that uh monica's view the negative
view of wisdom is very much tracking the
epicurean
form of enlightenment whereas the
positive form of wisdom is very much
tracking the stomach form of
enlightenment
now of course i'm going to argue as
always you need both
yes yeah you know you need
and you know we've had this conversation
elsewhere you need
to both be able to dial back
your own cognitive biases and reasoning
and things like that
and you know basically hold yourself at
bay
which is more the negative view of
wisdom but you also need to
have the shall we say you know
intellectual and existential courage to
reach out into the world to try and
change yeah so i'm going to sort of uh
sort of meta assimilation and meta
accommodation strategies in a sense yes
pretty much um
so then my you know my interest is okay
well how does the sense of realness play
into this
like especially realness of the
attainability of future states of view
um you know realness of certain
practices and things like that
and then the hope is to essentially take
the branch of my research that looks
at aspiration and wisdom
and future states of you as well as your
motivations behind why you're doing this
and stick it together with my research
on wisdom and spirituality
and magic to essentially say
you know if we give you a coherent
system for growth for self-transcendence
and you know
um despite my i think infamous among our
colleagues dislike of young
i think this is why people grab onto him
so tightly
is he gives you that he gives you that
in a slightly irresponsible
scattered and occluded kind of way which
is why i don't like him
um but he
gives you a narrative for growth and
development and unfortunately as we've
discussed
elsewhere so do conspiracy theories so
you need both and so i was going to ask
you maybe that
that'll be my final question for you
then we can wrap it up because
i'm just playing a little bit with the
etymology the word wizard which is
uh supposed to be you know is is an
archetypal name for
some sort of magic user also means wise
person
and i believe there's also connections
between the word wiccan
and wisdom in some fashion etymological
fashion too they all go back to the
um to the indo-european word for sight
right yeah and and so and
this is why um now this is why i don't
think wisdom is an effect of quality
wisdom is ultimately a capacity to
see possibilities yeah and
see the ultimate at the optimal route so
cited a sense of
insight rather than just visual i think
we've had this conversation before where
you can
you know wisdom seems to kind of be an
emergent function of insight hindsight
and foresight
yes i agree um where there's your
ability to look
deeply into a situation to see how it
came about and then to predict the
multiple ways in which it can unfold
yeah um so i'm a little bit more
interested you know i think
um you know nick west strait and uh
udith glick
um and you know michelle to an extent
have
the hindsight aspect of wisdom on walk
right and i think you and igor are
steadily getting into
and you know the lab in general still
getting into the insight
portion of wisdom right i'm kind of more
interested in the foresight
oh this is brilliant i hadn't seen it
that way before
oh that's very good june sun that's
really beautiful that's elegant
oh i like that that's oh that's very
very
oh wow that's very helpful thank you oh
what a gem to end on that's really
beautiful
yeah so you know this is where my
interest in like human ability to
predict the future
sense of realness the imagination and
things like that go because
i'm more interested in the aspects of
wisdom that have to do
with the actualization of possibility
shall we say yeah yeah that's very good
oh i like that that's really wonderful
well this has been fantastic and i
wanted to thank you for this
i don't know
it's hard to pull apart our work because
they're they're so interwoven
uh and you know and people have heard
your name in so many videos and you know
yeah episodes of awakening for the
meeting crisis yeah it's it's made
conferences interesting sometimes
i can imagine it could have been i i
think i've made this joke with you
before but you know people come up to me
at conferences and say
oh you have john vervinky's name on your
poster what's he like and he says you
realize that this is the guy who throws
boxes chocolate at me to get it out of
his apartment right like you know we
have a we have a very different working
relationship
one night what i deeply value so thank
you very much again i probably
uh would like you to have you on again
uh absolutely
and uh you know maybe maybe even a a
three-way dialogue with you and dan and
i or you and uh
anderson and i i think that would be
wonderful and so absolutely i think
i welcome you i welcome you back but
thank you very much for today it was
most excellent
oh yeah no this this was fun this was
fun and it's good talking to you as
always
thank you